A Finding Aid to the Andrew Dasburg and Grace Mott Johnson Papers, 1833-1980 (bulk 1900-1980), in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Andrew Dasburg Papers, circa 1900-1980; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 6 Linear feet Box 1-6
  - Alfred Dasburg Papers, 1914-1980; 1.7; Archival Resource Key
    Filed here are documents created by Alfred Dasburg, Andrew Dasburg and Grace Mott Johnson's son. Included is correspondence between Alfred Dasburg and family members, friends, his step-mother Nancy Lane, as well as with universities, art galleries, and museums regarding the loan of artwork by Andrew Dasburg or requesting biographical information about Dasburg or Johnson. A significant amount of correspondence during the late 1970s is with Virginia Gardner who was researching Dasburg and Johnson's careers and friendships with Louise Bryant. Also found within the correspondence are letters regarding his parents' health care. By the mid-1970s Alfred was handling many of his father's business and financial affairs which is reflected in these letters.
    Correspondence between Alfred and his father, Andrew Dasburg, is found in series 1.2, and correspondence between Alfred and his mother, Grace Mott Johnson, is found in series 2.2. Additional material in Alfred Dasburg's papers include three of his report cards, his wife Matilda's death certificate, and documents from his trip to Dasburg, Germany. Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
    - Alfred Dasburg Correspondence, 1914-1980; Archival Resource Key; (7 folders) (Box 6, Folder 35-41)
    - Report Cards, 1924, 1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Death Certificate for Matlilda Sevier Dasburg, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Documents from Trip to Dasburg, Germany, 1964; Archival Resource Key; (Not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Course Materials, Solid-State Electronics, 1967; Archival Resource Key; (Not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 45)
- Grace Mott Johnson Papers, 1833-1963; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 2.8 Linear feet Box 7-10
  The papers of Grace Mott Johnson document her personal life through extensive correspondence with family, friends, and fellow artists, as well as her writings, photographs and original artwork. To a lesser degree these papers document her career as an exhibiting sculptor and civil rights activist.
  Found within the Grace Mott Johnson papers are scattered biographical documents about the Grace and the Johnson families. Most of her papers consist of correspondence with family, including numerous letters to her son, Alfred Dasburg, friends, and fellow artists. Notable correspondents include John F. and Margaret Carlson, Florence Ballin Cramer, Jo Davidson, Florence Lucius, Walter Frankl, Lila Wheelock Howard, Henry Lee McFee, Mary Riley, Lee Simonson, Lindsey Morris Sterling, Alice Morgan Wright, Mabel Dodge Luhan, Vera Spier Kuhn, and others. Writings by Johnson include a very brief diary, poetry, her written account of two weeks in Taos, New Mexico, and other miscellaneous autobiographical writings. There are also a few writings by others. Scattered financial material includes receipts and account statements. Printed materials include one exhibition announcement and news clippings. Photographs are of Johnson, her family, friends, and works of art. Of note are photographs of Johnson with fellow artists, including a tintype of her with sculptors Florence Lucius and Jo Davidson. Johnson's artwork includes two folders of loose drawings and two sketchbooks, primarily of landscapes and animals.
  Almost all of this series has been scanned in its entirety. A few materials not scanned include scattered financial records and a printed booklet unrelated to art.
  The Grace Mott Johnson Papers series is arranged into 7 subseries:
  2.1: Biographical Material, 1833, circa 1888-1935
  2.2: Correspondence, 1854, 1882-1963
  2.3: Writings, 1848-1950
  2.4: Financial Material, 1911-1952
  2.5: Printed Material, 1882, 1917-1950
  2.6: Photographs, 1880s-1940
  2.7: Artwork, circa 1890-1928
  - Biographical Material, 1833, circa 1888-1935; 2.1; Archival Resource Key
    The small amount of biographical material found here includes Johnson family documents, such as list of births, as well as a draft of Grace Mott Johnson's will from 1912 and her brief biography for the publication "Leading Women of America." Legal documents include Johnson family property deeds and a legal agreement regarding Johnson's living accommodations while in Egypt. Also found are her Art Students' League membership card and three exhibition labels for her art work at the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts. Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
    - Grace Mott Johnson and Johnson Family Biographical Documents, circa 1888-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Johnson Family Legal Documents, 1833, 1924, 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Art Students League Membership Card, 1913; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Exhibition Labels, 1912; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1854, 1882-1963; 2.2; Archival Resource Key
    Eighty years of Johnson's general correspondence primarily consists of personal letters with friends, family, and fellow artists. There is also a substantial amount of correspondence with her son, Alfred Dasburg. The bulk of the correspondence dates from 1906 to 1919.
    Because Alfred spent most of his childhood living in Taos with his father, Andrew Dasburg, or away at school or camp, Johnson's correspondence with her son provides very candid and detailed accounts of her daily activities. The letters discuss her current artwork, news from her friends and relatives, and her travels, including her stay in Taos, New Mexico in 1919. Also included are numerous letters written during her stay in a mental hospital from 1937 to 1938. Many of her later letters to Alfred include reminiscences of her youth and extensive self-analysis.
    General correspondence with other family and friends is extensive and most often discusses social events, news of family and friends, and other daily activities of the writer. Family correspondence includes numerous letters between Johnson and her siblings, especially her brother Van Cleve Johnson. Grace Mott Johnson corresponded with numerous painter and sculptor friends whom she met at the Art Students' League and in Woodstock, New York. Some of these include Marion Bullard, Russell Cowles, John F. and Margaret Carlson, Florence Ballin Cramer, Florence Lucius, Walter Frankl, Lila Wheelock Howard, with whom she shared a studio for a period of time, Thomas Hunt, Henry Lee McFee, Morgan Russell, Mary Riley, Lee Simonson, Lindsey Morris Sterling, and Alice Morgan Wright. Johnson was also close friends with the Davidson family, and found here is her correspondence with the sculptor Jo Davidson and his two sisters Ray and Rose. Other notable correspondence is with friend Vera Spier Kuhn, wife of artist Walt Kuhn, art patron Mable Dodge Luhan, journalist John Reed, gallery owner William Macbeth, and her psychiatrist Abraham Brill. Also found is a small amount of correspondence documenting Johnson's civil rights activities, including letters from the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.
    This subseries also includes the correspondence of Frances H. Johnson, Grace Mott Johnson's aunt, also known as Aunt Fanny, with whom she was very close. Found here are postcards and letters from family and friends as well as numerous letters between Frances and Grace Mott Johnson, including several detailed letters from Grace describing her time in Taos.
    See Appendix B for a select list of correspondents from Series 2.2.
    Appendix B: Correspondents from Series 2.2: Grace Mott Johnson Papers, General Correspondence
    Barclay, Jessie: 1909
    Bercinsky, David: 1911, 1929, undated
    Bercinsky, Rachel: 1906, 1908
    Bigelow, Poultney: 1910, 1911, undated
    Borglum, Gutzon: 1908
    Bradenburgh, Margaret Caspar: 1908, 1910, 1911, 1915, 1916, 1919, 1940
    Brill, Abraham A.: 1919, 1921, 1935, 1937-40, 1948
    Bullard, Eleanor: 1909
    Bullard, Marion: 1911, 1912, undated
    Cahen, J. B.: 1907
    Carlson, John F. & Margaret: 1907-1913, 1921, 1947
    Comeau, Martin F.: 1943, 1944
    Cook, Charles Bayley: 1911
    Cowles, Russell: 1909
    Cramer, Florence Ballin: 1907-1912, 1947, undated
    D'Andrea, Cecelia (Cecil): 1907, 1912, 1921
    Dasburg, Margaret: 1908, 1909, 1912, undated
    Dasburg, Matilda: 1940
    Davidson, Jo: 1906-1910
    Davidson, Ray: 1906-1914, 1930, 1932, 1938, 1940-1942, 1951
    Davidson, Rose: 1906-1913
    de Kerstrat, Yvonne: 1909
    Debling, Anna J.: 1909
    Denman, George: 1917
    Doepel, C. Henry: 1922
    Drew, Aline: 1937, undated
    Durgy, Caroline R.: 1908
    Eberle, A.: 1930
    Edson, Helen: 1908
    Ennis, C.: 1910
    Frankl, Walter H.: 1915, 1918, 1919, undated
    Friends Intelligencer: 1936
    Frost, Chris: 1914
    Gardin, Laura: 1908
    Geiger, Mary: 1914, 1922
    Gilbert, Carl H.: 1927
    Harls, E. B.: 1908
    Holden, C.: 1950
    Howard, Lila Wheelock: 1908-1911, 1914, 1918, 1923, undated
    Humphrey, T. F.: 1910
    Hunt, Dorothy: 1911
    Hunt, Thomas: 1908 (illustrated letter)
    Hutchinson, Mary: 1937
    Illava, Agatha: 1933
    Isler, Jacques: 1933
    Jackson, Harrison S.: 1935
    Johnson, Alfred: 1907, 1908, 1911, 1914-1916
    Johnson, Francis: 1937, 1947
    Johnson, Mark: 1904, 1906, 1909, 1918, 1954
    Johnson, Van Cleve: 1904, 1908-1918, 1938, 1942, 1947, undated
    Kalish Pharmacy: 1910
    Kleinert, H.: 1923
    Kuhn, Vera Spier: 1908-1912
    Labaree, Mary Fleming: 1931
    Lane, Mrs. Franklin: 1933
    Law, Ellen M.: 1910, 1912, 1922
    Lincoln University: 1931
    Lucius, Albert: 1922
    Lucius, Florence (Floss): 1908-1915, undated
    Luhan, Mabel Dodge: 1919, 1924, 1933
    Macbeth, William: 1911
    Macomb, Edith: 1920
    Macrum, Mrs. George: 1947
    Magee, R.: 1909, 1910
    Martin, Daniel S.: 1891
    McFee, Henry Lee: 1912, 1914, undated
    McKenzie, Ilya: 1909-1911
    Miles, John E.: 1938
    Milner, H. W.: 1910
    Morgan, Helen: 1907, 1908, 1911, 1912
    Morrell, Edith: 1910, 1911, undated
    Morton-Morris, Mrs. John: 1946
    Mott, Cora E.: 1908
    Mott, Jane: 1910
    Mott, Laura: 1894, 1906-1908
    National Association for the Advancement of Colored People: 1935-1937, 1940, undated
    National Association of Woment Painters and Sculptors: 1937
    The New York News: 1935
    Noyes, Minnie A.: 1916
    Odok, Effiom: 1938
    Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts: 1913
    Pfeiffer, J.: 1912
    Potterat, Mathilda: 1910, 1912
    Radcliffe, C. M. R.: 1912
    Raub, Ida: 1922
    Reed, John: 1916
    Reynolds, William E.: 1922
    Riley, Mary: 1909-1911, undated
    Rogers, Julia J.: 1911
    Rosenberg, Elfie Cahen: 1904-1912, 1926
    Russell, Morgan: 1908
    Schlisinger, Gisela: 1907
    Schuyler, Josephine: 1933
    Scott, Leon W.: 1935
    Sholtz, David: 1935
    Simkins, Martha: 1913
    Simonson, Lee: 1912, 1914-1917, 1928, undated
    Smith, S. Archibald: 1920
    Spanish and Indian Trading Co.: 1926
    Sterling, Lindsey Morris (Sally): 1908-1912
    Sutherland, Arthur: 1936-1939
    Teague, Cecil: 1911
    Teague, Walter: 1911
    Wardwell, James: 1909
    Watkins, Mary Jane: 1930
    Weeks, Henry de F.: 1910
    Weigand, Margarith: 1909-1914
    White, Mrs. John K.: 1908
    Wright, Alice Morgan: 1907, 1908, 1910, 1930
    Yaldo, Margaret: 1917-1919
    - Correspondence with Alfred Dasburg, 1914-1925; Archival Resource Key; (6 folders) (Box 7, Folder 5-10)
    - Correspondence with Alfred Dasburg, 1931-1963; Archival Resource Key; (6 folders) (Box 7, Folder 11-16)
    - General Correspondence, circa 1882-1894, 1901-1907; Archival Resource Key; (6 folders) (Box 7, Folder 17-22)
    - General Correspondence, 1908; Archival Resource Key; (6 folders) (Box 7, Folder 23-28)
    - General Correspondence, 1909; Archival Resource Key; (7 folders) (Box 7, Folder 29-35)
    - General Correspondence, 1910; Archival Resource Key; (5 folders) (Box 7, Folder 36-40)
    - General Correspondence, 1911; Archival Resource Key; (7 folders) (Box 8, Folder 1-7)
    - General Correspondence, 1912-1914; Archival Resource Key; (10 folders) (Box 8, Folder 8-17)
    - General Correspondence, 1915-1932; Archival Resource Key; (8 folders) (Box 8, Folder 18-25)
    - General Correspondence, 1933-1954; Archival Resource Key; (7 folders) (Box 8, Folder 26-32)
    - General Correspondence, Undated Letters, A-Z, circa 1900-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - General Correspondence, Letter Fragments and Drafts, circa 1940-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - General Correspondence, Unidentified, circa 1900-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Frances H. Johnson Correspondence, 1887-1909; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders) (Box 8, Folder 36-38)
    - Frances H. Johnson Correspondence, 1910-1919, 1930; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders) (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
    - Ebenezer Alfred Johnson Letter, 1854; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Writings, 1848-1950; 2.3; Archival Resource Key
    Found here are writings by Grace Mott Johnson and others. Writings by Johnson include two brief autobiographical writings describing her early life, such as living on a farm, her interest in art, and her art education. Also found is a diary giving an account of her daily activities for one week in 1904, various handwritten recipes and menus, and several issues of "The Johnson Monthly" a home-made magazine written by Grace and her siblings and illustrated by Grace. Of particular interest is a writing entitled "Two Weeks in New Mexico," Johnson's detailed account of her stay in a cottage belonging to Mabel Dodge Luhan in Taos, New Mexico, their attempt to attend an Indian dance, and her interaction with Andrew Dasburg while there. Additional miscellaneous writings by Johnson include poems, writings about civil rights, loose diary-style writings in which she expresses her thoughts on her early life and experiences with psychoanalysis, notes, lists, and other writing fragments, some of which may be draft letters. Writings by others include a draft of an address on natural history given by her relative John Van Cleve, poetry by others, and an essay "Shall Women Vote?" by an unidentified author. Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
    - Writings by Grace Mott Johnson, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
      - Autobiographical Writings, 1913, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Diary, March 27-April 2, 1904; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - "The Johnson Monthly,", June 1899-May 1903; Archival Resource Key; (4 folders) (Box 9, Folder 7-10)
      - "Two Weeks in New Mexico,", 1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Recipes and Menus, circa 1910s, 1919; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Miscellaneous Writings, 1896-1940, 1947; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders) (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
    - Writings by Others, Archival Resource Key (Box 10)
      - Dr. John Van Cleve, Address to His Colleagues, circa mid-1800s; Archival Resource Key; (Not scanned) (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Miscellaneous Writings, 1848-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Financial Material, 1911-1952; 2.4; Archival Resource Key
    A small amount of financial material includes receipts for the delivery or casting of Johnson's sculptures and for the purchase of art supplies. Miscellaneous financial records primarily include account statements. Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
    - Receipts, 1911-1914; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Financial Records, 1924-1952; Archival Resource Key; (Not scanned) (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Printed Material, 1882, 1917-1950; 2.5; Archival Resource Key
    Printed material includes a booklet containing essays on religion, an announcement for the exhibition of Johnson's artwork, and various news clippings of articles on the exhibition of her artwork and her civil rights activities. Miscellaneous printed material includes clippings of published poems and song lyrics by others and two Ringling Bros. Circus route schedules. Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
    - Booklet, A Word: He That Has Ears, Let Him Hear, 1882; Archival Resource Key; (Not scanned) (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Exhibition Announcement, 1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - News Clippings, 1935-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - News Clippings, Undated, circa 1935-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1917-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, 1880s-1940; 2.6; Archival Resource Key
    Found here are photographs of Grace Mott Johnson, her family, friends, and artwork. Photographs of Johnson include a portrait of her as a small child and portraits of her as a young woman, as well as photographs of her in Yonkers, New York, on Monhegan Island in Maine, and in Taos, New Mexico. Also found are nude photographs of Johnson at the beach and bathing in a river, and photographs of her with her son Alfred. Photographs of Johnson with friends include a tintype of her with the artists Jo Davidson and Florence Lucius, another photograph of her with Lucius, with her friend and fellow artist Lila Wheelock Howard, with fellow artists Edward McCartan, Walter Frankl, and Carl Illava, and dining with various friends including the artist Henry Lee McFee. Also found here are a few photographs of other friends and family, and photographs of her artwork. Additional photographs of Johnson with Andrew Dasburg and others are found in Dasburg's papers, Series 1.5. Photographs are arranged by subject and chronologically within each folder.
    - Photographs of Grace Mott Johnson, 1880s-1924; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Nude Photographs of Grace Mott Johnson, circa 1910s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Photographs of Grace Mott Johnson with Alfred Dasburg, circa 1911-1921; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Photographs of Grace Mott Johnson with Friends, circa 1908-1910s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Photographs of Friends and Family, 1922, 1932-1933, Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Photographs of Artwork by Grace Mott Johnson, circa 1910-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Artwork, circa 1890-1928; 2.7; Archival Resource Key
    This subseries contains artwork by Grace Mott Johnson, including loose drawings and two sketchbooks. Loose drawings include pen and ink drawings of horses and illustrations of animals and landscapes in pencil and charcoal for "The Johnson Monthly," a home-made magazine created by Johnson and her siblings. The sketchbook dating from circa 1901 to 1902 contains charcoal and pencil drawings of animals, landscapes, and other designs. The sketchbook from circa 1911 includes two pencil sketches of her son Alfred Van Cleve Dasburg, as well as drawings of animals and preliminary sketches for her sculptures. Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
    - Drawings, circa 1890, 1902-1903, 1927-1928; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 19-20)
    - Sketchbook, circa 1901-1902; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Sketchbook, circa 1911; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 22)